Actually, I was like a mother to them from My very childhood.
दरअसल, अपने बचपन से ही मैं उनके लिए माँ जैसी थी।
When My father, mother went to jail, I was, first time I was about, I think,
जब मेरे पिता, माता जेल गए, मैं थी, मुझे लगता है, पहली बार मैं थी, करीब
five and a half years of age, so I had all the keys of the house in My little frock
साढ़े पांच साल की उम्र की, तो मेरे पास, मेरी छोटी फ्रॉक में, घर की चाबियां थीं
thing and I used to carry all the duties like a grandmother. I never felt lost,
और मैं सभी कर्तव्यों का पालन एक दादी की तरह करती थी। मैंने कभी स्वयं को खोया हुआ महसूस नहीं किया,
I mean, My life is on the whole, is very collective by temperament, I'm extremely collective.
मेरा मतलब, मेरा जीवन कुल मिलाकर, स्वभाव से बहुत सामूहिक है, मैं बेहद सामूहिक हूं।
I can live anywhere, I can sleep anywhere, I can live in the jungles, I can - I have
मैं कहीं भी रह सकतीं हूँ, मैं कहीं भी सो सकतीं हूँ, मैं जंगलों में रह सकतीं हूँ, मैं कर सकतीं हूँ - मुझे
no problems of that, I'm extremely collective. I'm not exclusive by temperament
उस की कोई समस्या नहीं है, मैं अत्यंत सामूहिक हूँ। मैं बहुत बचपन से स्वभाव से विशिष्ट नहीं हूँ।
from very childhood. I was very friendly with all the people in that area, where we
मैं उस क्षेत्र के सभी लोगों के साथ बहुत मिलनसार थी, जहाँ हम
were living and My mother was known as Nirmala's mother, father was known as
रह रहे थे और मेरी माँ को निर्मला की माँ के रूप में जाना जाता था और पिता को निर्मला के पिता के नाम से जाना जाता था।
Nirmala's father, so they said, "We have lost our identity because of Her."
तो उन्होंने कहा, "हमने तो इनकी वजह से अपनी पहचान खो दी है।"
So, I was a very friendly person. I never felt lonely and when I'm with Myself,
इसलिए मैं बहुत मिलनसार इंसान थी। मुझे कभी अकेलापन महसूस नहीं हुआ और जब मैं अपने साथ होतीं हूँ
I'm never lonely at all. I enjoy Myself very much. [SHRI MATAJI LAUGHS]
मैं कभी अकेली नहीं होती। मैं स्वयं का बहुत अधिक आनंद लेतीं हूँ। [श्री माताजी हंसती हैं]